# **Ira James Watt**

(+44)7508 116845 | irawatt.co.uk | irawatt@gmail.com | NE24BA

#### Personal Statement

I am a recent Newcastle University graduate with two years of full-stack software development experience and have an enthusiasm for data science. I graduated with a BSc Hon 1st in Computer Science, achieving an 80% average. I've worked with various technologies including, Google Analytics, SQL Server Management Studio, Python ML, and Power BI. Just recently, I completed a DataCamp course in fraud detection in Python. I also just finished a project building a machine learning model to forecasted national electricity demand.

# Work Experience

#### Junior Developer - The North of England P&I Association Limited

2020-Present

**Responsibilities:** Provide third line support across the business, primarily working on reporting, developing the company's policy management system, and maintaining ETL pipelines in SSIS.

**Achievements:** Led automation around currency exchange rate information, saving countless business hours. Created custom Power BI reporting around the service desk, improving the cohesion between the business and development team.

# Applications Developer Placement - Newcastle University IT

2018-2019

**Responsibilities:** Develop applications for both student and academic bodies.

**Achievements:** Led the development of the university's new scanner attendance web service. Successfully advanced and deployed versions of the university app and library desktop app. Trained new placements.

# Education

# Newcastle University - BSc Hon 1st in Computer Science with Industrial Placement

2016-2020

Achieved a first class in my 'Biologically Inspired Computing' module in which I trained multiple machine learning models in classification based tasks. Participated in Hackathons. Acted as lead developer in team project building an Android app. Active in the NUOTC (Northumbrian Universities Officers Training Corps).

#### **DataCamp** - Fraud Detection in Python

2020-2020

Covered data resampling methods, supervised/unsupervised models, and text mining for fraud detection.

LinkedIn Learning - Excel Essential Training, Data Science Fundamentals and Learning Data Governance 2020-2020

**Prudhoe Community High School** - 3 A-Levels & 12 GCSEs

2012-2016

## Personal Projects

#### **National Demand Model** (Python – Sklearn, Numpy, Matplotlib & Pandas)

2020-2021

The model, back with strong analysis, uses multilinear regression to predict the national energy demand. The data used includes historical ND (national demand) data gathered from the National Grid ESO and London's daily average temperature scraped from weather.com to make its predictions. Full documentation on GitHub.

#### Algo2k 🔼 (PWA, Node.js, Python – Matplotlib & Pandas, Firebase)

2019-2020

Developed as part of my dissertation, Algo2k is a web app designed to perform validation/backtesting on Python-based algorithmic trading strategies. The site standardised the validation process to reduces biases such as survivorship, optimization, and look ahead biases.

# **Web Portfolio** (Angular2, Chart.js, Three.js, JQuery, Bootstrap, Firebase)

2019-2019

The site showcases much of my work at university and on placement. The full version is available on desktop.

## **Contributions and Interests**

- **Stack Overflow** 1,500 Reputation with over 50 questions answered (stackoverflow.com/users/10053793).
- \* National Citizen Service Helped improve local communities in my home area.
- Other Hobbies I enjoy strategy games, running and gym.

# **Proficiencies**

Excel •••• Python ••• SQL ••• Azure ML ••• Power BI ••• R ••••

github.com/wisespira Irawatt.co.uk linkedin.com/in/ira-watt